In 2007,
في 2007
I decided that we needed to reconceptualize
قررت اننا نحتاج لاعادة النظر في المفاهيم
how we thought about economic development.
حول كيف تفكيرنا في التطور الاقتصادي
Our new goal should be
هدفنا الجديد يجب ان يكون
that when every family thinks about where they want to live and work,
انه عندما تفكر كل اسرة اين تريد ان تعيش وتعمل,
they should be able to choose between
يجب ان يكون لديهم الخيار بين
at least a handful
على الاقل في متناول اليد
of different cities
مدن مختلفة
that were all competing to attract new residents.
حيث نتنافس جميعنا في اجتذاب سكان جدد
Now we're a long way away from that goal right now.
نحن الان بعيدين بمسافات من ذلك الهدف.
There are billions of people in developing countries
هناك البلايين من الناس في الدول النامية
who don't have even a single city that would be willing to welcome them.
ممن لا يوجد لديهم حتى ولو مدينة واحدة ترحب بهم.
But the amazing thing about cities
لكن الشيء المدهش بخصوص المدن
is they're worth so much more
انها تساوي اكثر بكثير
than it costs to build them.
من التكاليف اللازمة لبنائها.
So we could easily supply the world
وبالتالي يمكننا ببساطة تزويد العالم
with dozens, maybe hundreds,
بالعشرات او ربما المئات,
of new cities.
من المدن الجديدة.
Now this might sound preposterous to you
ربما بدى لكم ذلك غير معقول
if you've never thought about new cities.
اذا كنتم لم تفكرو من قبل بالمدن الجديدة.
But just substitute apartment building for cities.
لكن فقط استبدلو البنايات السكنية بالمدن.
Imagine half the people who wanted to be in apartments already had them;
تخيل ان نصف الناس الراغبين في الحصول على شقق سكنية, قد حصلو عليها فعلا
the other half aren't there yet.
النصف الاخر مازال بالانتظار
You could try and expand the capacity
يمكنك محاول توسيع الطاقة الاستيعابية
by doing additions on all the existing apartments.
بعمل العديد من الاضافات على الشقق الحالية.
But you know what you'd run into
لكن تعلم ما أنت مقبل عليه
is those apartments and the surrounding areas
هل تلك الشقق والمناطق المحيطة بها
have rules to avoid discomfort
قد استوفت الشروط الازمة لتفادي عدم الراحة
and the distractions of construction.
والعيوب الانشائية.
So it's extremely hard to do all of those additions.
لذلك من الصعب عمل كل تلك الاضافات.
But you could go out someplace brand new,
لكن بامكانك الذهاب الى مكان اخر جديد كليا,
build a brand new apartment building,
وتبني عمارة سكنية جديدة,
as long as the rules there
طالما كانت الشروط مستوفاة.
were ones that facilitated construction
حيث من شانها تسهيل الانشاء
rather than getting in the way.
بدلا من ان تدخلنا في متاهات.
So I proposed
لذلك اقترحت
that governments create new reform zones
ان تقوم الحكومات بانشاء من مناطق مستصلحة جديدة
big enough to hold cities
كبيرة بما يكفي لتحتضن مدن
and gave them a name: charter cities.
واعطائها تسمية : مدن الامتياز.
Later I learned that at about this same time,
لاحقا علمت انه تقريبا في نفس الوقت,
Javier and Octavio
جافير و اوكتافو
were thinking about the challenge of reform
كانا يفكران في تحدي الاصلاح
in Honduras.
في الهندوراس
They knew that about 75,000 Hondurans every year
لقد علما ان هناك حوالي 75000 مواطن هندوراسي في كل عام
would leave to go to the United States,
يغادرون في اتجاه الولايات المتحدة
and they wanted to ask, what could they do
وكانا يتساءلان مالذي يمكنهما عمله
to make sure that those people could stay
لضمان ان اؤلائك المهاجرين سوف يبقون
and do the same things in Honduras.
ويقومون بنفس الاعمال في الهندوراس.
At one point, Javier said to Octavio,
في لحظة ما , جافيير قال لاوكتافيو,
"What if we took some of our empty land --
"ماذا لو اخذنا بعضا من ارضينا الفارغة --
what if we just gave it to an embassy --
ماذا لو اعطيناها لسفارة --
give some to the U.S. embassy; give some to the Canadian embassy --
نعطي بعضها للسفارة الامريكية , والبعض للسفارة الكندية--
and then if people want to go work
ومن ثم اذا اراد الناس الذهاب للعمل
under the rules of Canada or under the rules of the United States,
تحت انظمة كندا او انظمة الولايات المتحدة,
they can go get jobs,
بامكانهم الذهاب والحصول على وظائف ,
do everything they do on those embassy grounds
ويعملون كل ما يعملونه في اراضي السفارة
that they would otherwise have to go to Canada or the U.S. to do?"
والذي في المقابل كان يتوجب عليهم السفر الى كندا للقيام به؟"
In the summer of 2009,
في صيف 2009
Honduras went through a wrenching constitutional crisis.
مرت الهندوراس بازمة دستورية موجعة.
At the next regularly scheduled election,
وفي الموعد المعتاد للانتخابات,
Pepe Lobo won in a landslide
بيبي لوبو فاز باغلبية ساحقة
on a platform that promised reform,
بالاعتماد على برنامج انتخابي وعد بالاصلاح,
but reconciliation as well.
والمصالحة ايضا
He asked Octavio to be his chief of staff.
لقد طلب من اوكتافيو ان يكون مدير فريق العمل.
Meanwhile, I was getting ready
خلال ذلك. كنت استعد
to give a talk at TEDGlobal.
لالقاء كحاضرة في تيد جلوبال.
Through a process of refinement,
من خلال عملية من التنقيح,
trial and error, a lot of user testing,
التجربة والخطأ, العديد من الاختبارات,
I tried to boil this complicated concept of charter city
حاولت تبسيط هذا المفهوم المعقد لمدن الامتياز
down to the bare essentials.
الى مستوى الاساسيات المجردة
The first point was the importance of rules,
النقطة الاولى كانت اهمية الشروط,
like those rules that say
كتلك الشروط التي تقول
you can't come in and disturb all the existing apartment holders.
لايمكنك القدوم وازعاج كل ملاك الشقق الموجودين.
We pay a lot of attention to new technologies,
اهتممنا كثيرا بالتكنلوجيا الحديثة,
but it takes technologies and rules to get progress,
لكن استلزم الامر الاخذ بالتكنلوجيا والشروط لانجاز العمل
and it's usually the rules that hold us back.
ودائما ما كانت الشروط تستوقفنا
In the fall of 2010, a friend from Guatemala
في خريف 2010 , صديق من جواتيمالا
sent Octavio a link to the TEDTalk.
ارسل الى اوكتافيو رابط تيدتوك.
He showed it to Javier.
وعرضه على جافير.
They called me.
اتصلا بي.
They said, "Let's present this to the leaders of our country."
قالا" لنقم بعرض هذا الموضوع على قادة الدولة"
So in December we met in Miami,
في ديسمبر التقينا في ميامي,
in a hotel conference room.
في غرفة اجتماعات في احد الفنادق
I tried to explain this point
حاولت شرح هذه النقطة
about how valuable cities are,
حول كم هي قيمة تلك المدن,
how much more valuable they are than they cost.
كم هي قيمة اكثر بكثير من تكاليف انشائها.
And I used this slide
واستخدمت هذا الرسم التوضيحي
showing how valuable the raw land is
ليبين كم هي قيمة هذه الاراضي الخام
in a place like New York City:
في مكان مثل مدينة نيويورك.
notice, land that's worth thousands of dollars, in some cases,
لاحظ,اراض تساوي الاف الدولارات , في بعض الحالات,
per square meter.
للمتر المربع.
But it was a fairly abstract discussion,
لكن كنت وبكل امانة اجرد النقاش,
and at some point when there was a pause,
وفي بعض اللحظات حيث كان هناك توقف,
Octavio said,
قال اوكتافيو,
"Paul, maybe we could watch the TEDTalk."
"بول, لربما يمكننا مشاهدة تيد توك"
(Laughing)
"ضحك"
So the TEDTalk laid out in very simple terms,
اذا تيد توك عرض بمصطلحات بسيطة جدا,
a charter city is a place
مدينة الامتياز هي مكان
where you start with uninhabited land,
حيث تبدا بارض غير مأهولة,
a charter that specifies the rules that will apply there
امتياز يحدد القواعد التي سيتم اتباعها في ذلك المكان
and then a chance for people to opt in,
ومن ثم فرصة للناس للاختيار,
to go live under those rules or not.
ان يذهبو ويعيشو تحت تلك الشروط او لا.
So I was asked by the president of Honduras
لذلك سئلت من قبل رئيس الهندوراس
who said that we need to do this project,
من قال اننا علينا القيام بهذا المشروع,
this is important,
هذا مهم,
this could be the way forward for our country.
قد يكون هذا طريق تقدم بلدنا.
I was asked to come to Tegucigalpa
طلب مني ان احضر الى تيجوسجالبا
and talk again on January fourth and fifth.
والحديث مرة اخرى في الرابع والخامس من يناير.
So I presented
لذلك قدمت
another fact-filled lecture
محاضرة اخرى ملئية بالحقائق
that included a slide like this,
والتي احتوت رسما كهذا,
which tried to make the point that, if you want to create a lot of value in a city,
والذي حاولت ان يبين النقطة انه اذا اردت ان تضيف المزيد من القيمة في المدينة,
it has to be very big.
يجب ان تكون كبيرة جدا.
This is a picture of Denver,
هذه صورة لد دينفر,
and the outline is the new airport that was built in Denver.
والنقطة الرئيسية هي المطار الجديد الذي تم انشاءه في دينفر.
This airport alone
المطار وحده
covers more than 100 square kilometers.
يغطي اكثر من 100 كيلو متر مربع.
So I was trying to persuade the Hondurans,
لذلك كنت احاول اقناع الهوندوراسيين
if you build a new city,
اذا بنيتم مدينة جديدة,
you've got to start with a site that's at least 1,000 square kilometers.
يجب عليكم البدا بموقع لا يقل عن 1000 كيلو متر مربع.
That's more than 250 hundred-thousand acres.
ذلك اكثر من 250 الف فدان.
Everybody applauded politely.
الجميع صفق بأدب.
The faces in the audience
وجوه الحاضرين
were very serious and attentive.
كانت جادة وحاضرة الذهن.
The leader of the congress came up on stage and said,
رئيس البرلمان صعد الى المنصة وقال,
"Professor Romer, thank you very much for your lecture,
"بروفسور رومر, اشكرك جدا على هذه المحاضرة,
but maybe we could watch the TEDTalk.
لكن ربما يمكننا مشاهدة تيد توك.
I've got it here on my laptop."
انها معي على جاهزي المحمول"
So I sat down, and they played the TEDTalk.
فقمت بالجلوس وقامو بتشغيل مقطع تيد توك.
And it got to the essence,
وقد احتوى الخلاصة,
which is that a new city could offer new choices for people.
ان المدن الجديدة سوف تمنح المزيد من الفرص للناس.
There would be a choice of a city which you could go to
سيكون هناك خيار لمدينة يمكنك الذهاب اليها
which could be in Honduras,
والتي ستكون في الهندوراس,
instead of hundreds of miles away in the North.
بدلا من الاف الاميال شمالا.
And it also involved new choices for leaders.
وايضا تضمنت خيارات جديدة للقادة.
Because the leaders in the government there in Honduras
لان القادة في الحكومة هناك في الهندوراس
would need help from partner countries,
سوف يحتاجون المساعدة من الدول المشاركة
who could benefit from partner countries
والتي يمكنها الاستفادة من الدول الشريكة
who help them set up the rules in this charter and the enforcement,
نحن نساعدهم لوضع القواعد في هذا الامتياز وتطبيقه,
so everybody can trust
بحيث ان كل شخص يستطيع الوثوق
that the charter really will be enforced.
ان الامتياز سيتم تطبيقه حقيقة
And the insight of President Lobo
وبصيرة الرئيس لوبو
was that that assurance of enforcement
هي ضمانة ذلك التبطبيق
that I was thinking about
ذلك ما كنت افكر به
as a way to get the foreign investors to come in and build the city
كطريقة لجلب مستثمرين من الخارج لبناء مدينة
could be equally important for all the different parties in Honduras
يمكن ان يكون على قدر متساو من الاهمية لجميع الاطراف المختلفة في الهندوراس
who had suffered for so many years
الذين كانو يعانون لاعوام طويلة
from fear and distrust.
من الارتياب وعدم الثقة.
We went and looked at a site.
ذهبنا والقينا نظرة على الموقع.
This picture's from there.
هذه الصورة من هناك.
It easily could hold a thousand square kilometers.
من السهولة ان تستوعب الاف الكيلومترات المربعة
And shortly thereafter, on January 19th,
وبعد ذلك الحين بفترة قصيرة, في التاسع عشر من يناير,
they voted in the congress to amend their constitution
صوتوا في البرلمان على تعديل دستورهم
to have a constitutional provision
للحصول على بند دستوري
that allows for special development regions.
يخول انشاء مناطق خاصة
In a country which had just gone through this wrenching crisis,
في دولة خاضت للتو ازمة مريعة,
the vote in the congress in favor of this constitutional amendment
التصويت في البرلمان في ما يخص هذا التعدي الدستوري
was 124 to one.
كان 124 الى واحد
All parties, all factions in society, backed this.
جميع الاطراف, جميع الفصائل في المجتمع , دعمت هذا
To be part of the constitution, you actually have to pass it twice in the congress.
ليكون جزء من الدستور, يجب عليك تمرريره مرتين في البرلمان
On February 17th they passed it again
في السابع عشر من فبراير مرره مجددا
with another vote of 114 to one.
وحصل على 114 الى واحد.
Immediately after that vote,
مباشرة بعد ذلك التصويت,
on February 21st to the 24th,
في الحادي والعشرين من فبراير والى الرابع والعشرين من نفس الشهر
a delegation of about 30 Hondurans
وفد من 30 هندوراسي
went to the two places in the world
ذهبوا الى مكانين في العالم
that are most interested in getting into the city building business.
هما الاكثر اهتماما بسوق بناء المدن.
One is South Korea.
الاولى هي كوريا الجنوبية
This is a picture of a big, new city center
هذه صورة لمركز مدينة كبير وجديد
that's being built in South Korea --
والذي تم بناؤه في كوريا الجنوبية--
bigger than downtown Boston.
اكبر من وسط البلد في بوستن.
Everything you see there was built in four years,
كل ما تراه هناك تم بناؤه في اربعة سنين,
after they spent four years getting the permits.
بعد ان امضو اربعة سنين حصلوا على التصاريح
The other place that's very interested in city building is Singapore.
المكان الاخر المهتم جدا ببناء المدن هو سينغافورة.
They've actually built two cities already in China
في الواقع قد قاموا ببناء مدينتين في الصين
and are preparing the third.
ويحضرون للثالثة
So if you think about this practically,
لذلك اذا فكرت في ذلك عمليا,
here's where we are.
ها نحن ذا.
They've got a site; they're already thinking about this site for the second city.
لديهم موقع, وهم فعليا يفكرون في هذا الموقع للمدينة الثانية.
They're putting in place a legal system
يحضرون نظاما تشريعيا
that could allow for managers to come in,
من شأنه ان يخول المدراء ان يحضروا
and also an external legal system.
وايضا نظام تشريعي خارجي.
One country has already volunteered to let its supreme court
احدى الدول قامت بالتطوع لجعل محكمتها العليا
be the court of final appeal for the new judicial system there.
ان تكون هي محكمة الاستئناف في النظام القضائي هناك.
There's designers and builders of cities
هناك مصممون وبناءون للمدن
who are very interested.
هم جدا مهتمين.
They even can bring with them some financing.
يستطيعين ايضا جلب بعض الاستثمارات معهم.
But the one thing you know they've already solved
لكن هناك شيئا واحدا قد قامو بمعالجته
is that there's lots of tenants.
انه هناك العديد من المستاجرين.
There's lots of businesses that would like to locate in the Americas,
هناك الكثير من الاعمال تريد ان تكون في امريكا,
especially in a place with a free trade zone,
خصوصا في مناطق التجارة الحرة,
and there's lots of people who'd like to go there.
وهناك العديد من من الناس يرغبون ان يكونو هناك.
Around the world, there's 700 million people
حول العالم هناك 700 مليون شخص
who say they'd like to move permanently someplace else right now.
يقولون انه يرغبون في الانتقال نهائيا الى مكان اخر خالا.
There's a million a year
هناك مليون كل سنة
who leave Latin America to go to the United States.
يغادرون امريكا الاتينية في اتجاه الولايات المتحدة
Many of these are a father
الكثير منهم آباء
who has to leave his family behind to go get a job --
ترك خلفه عائلة للبحث عن وظيفة --
sometimes a single mother
وبعض الاحيان ام وحيدة
who has to get enough money to even pay for food or clothing.
يتوجب عليها الحصول على المال الكافي لدفع نفقات الاكل والملبس
Sadly, sometimes there are even children
وللاسف بعض الاحيان هناك اطفال
who are trying to get reunited with their parents
يحاولون الاجتماع بابائهم
that they haven't seen, in some cases, for a decade.
الذين لم يروهم , في بعض الاحيان لعقد من الزمان.
So what kind of an idea is it
اذا اي نوع من الافكار هي
to think about building a brand new city in Honduras?
ان تفكر في بناء مدينة جديدة في الهندوراس؟
Or to build a dozen of these,
او ان تبني العشرات منها,
or a hundred of these, around the world?
او المئات منها حول العالم؟
What kind of an idea is it
اي نوع من الافكار هي
to think about insisting
ان نفكر بمنح
that every family have a choice of several cities
كل عائلة الخيار بين عدد من المدن
that are competing to attract new residents?
التي تتنافس لاجتذاب السكان الجدد؟
This is an idea worth spreading.
هذه فكرة تستحق النشر.
And my friends from Honduras
واصدقائي من الهندوراس
asked me to say thank you, TED.
طلبو مني ان اقول شكر لك يا تيد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)